Guide to the Brooklyn scrapbooks collection ARC.247
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn scrapbooks collection
circa 1840 to 1979
Brooklyn Historical Society
Mercier, Helen Cory
Nickerson, Herman
Frost, Josephine C.
Hoag, Spencer
Havemeyer, Loomis
ARC.247
7.2 Linear Feet in two record cartons, six flat boxes and two volumes.
The Brooklyn scrapbooks collection consists of 22 volumes containing ephemeral materials documenting several subjects in Brooklyn from the 1840s to the 1970s.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Portions of the collection were the gift of Laura M. Brewster, Don Fina, Josephine C. Frost, Spencer Hoag, Helen Cory Mercier, and William A. Robbins, and Gabriel Harrison, dates unknown. Sources and dates of acquisition for remaining scrapbooks in the collection are unknown.
Existence and Location of Copies
The Brooklyn Theatre Fire scrapbook by Augustus Toedteberg has been photocopied for access and is available in the library under the call number F129.B7 B768 1876p.
Arrangement
This is an artifical collection and there is no formal arrangement.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Theatre Fire Relief Association Records (1977.049)
Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection (ARC.212)
Henry F. Minton scrapbook (1977.271)
Plymouth Church publications and ephemera (1986.019)
Brooklyn Republican Party scrapbook (1977.077)
Bloodgood H. Cutter autograph (1974.240)
Brooklyn Playbills and Programs Collection (BCMS.0041): Park Theatre
Frank Jenks theater program collection (1992.023)
May B. Woodward scrapbook (1977.292)
Brooklyn theater collection (1977.041)
Kings County Historical Society records (ARC.058)
Scope and Contents
Subjects include the Henry Ward Beecher adultery trial of 1875, the Brooklyn Theatre fire of 1876, the Coney Island Mardi Gras celebrations of 1913 and 1924, the 1935 proposition of the New York City and Long Island parkway system, World War I and World War II, the Prospect Park centennial in 1966, and several additional topics generally relating to history, business, politics, genealogy, and social and cultural life in Brooklyn, Long Island, and New York City. Compilers of the scrapbooks include Josephine C. Frost, Spencer Hoag, Helen Cory Mercier, and Herman Nickerson, though the origins of many of the scrapbooks are unknown. Materials in the scrapbooks include clippings and obituaries (many from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle newspaper), programs, pamphlets, menus, magazines, invitations and announcements, press releases, theater playbills, poems, postcards, illustrations, cartoons, and photographs. Also included is a scrapbook documenting a 1902 trip to Europe taken by Brooklyn resident Loomis Havemeyer (1886-1971) and his family.
Pamphlets; Correspondence; Picture postcards; Illustrations (layout features); Genealogy; Photographs; Programs (documents); Playbills; Families |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Menus; Obituaries; Press releases; Clippings (information artifacts); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Intellectual life; Scrapbooks; Maps; Poems; History |x Societies, etc.; World War, 1914-1918; Centennial celebrations, etc.; World War, 1939-1945; Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Real property |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parkways |z New York (State) |z New York; Parkways |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Voyages and travels; Printed ephemera; Magazines (periodicals); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Trials (Adultery) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Long Island (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.); Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fires |x Casualties |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Theaters |x Fires and fire prevention |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Europe |x Description and travel; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Theaters |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Theater |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Kings County Historical Society; Prospect Park Centennial Committee; Coney Island Carnival Company (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). Executive Committee; Frost, Josephine C.; Cutter, Bloodgood H. (Bloodgood Haviland); Cory, Maude Wilson; Beecher, Henry Ward
- A Brief History of Maude Wilson Cory, Mercier, Helen Cory (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Newspaper clippings related to Brooklynite Maude Wilson Cory (1879-1964), "who was prominent in business and politics."
  Cory, Maude Wilson
- Personal scrapbook of Josephine C. Frost, Frost, Josephine C. (Box 1)
  Biographical Note
  Josephine C. Frost was a genealogist who lived in Brooklyn.
  Correspondence, clippings and photographs related to Frost's life and family.
- Scrapbook of poems from different sources, 1870 July 6; Nickerson, Herman (Box 1)
  Collected by Herman Nickerson, Northport, Long Island and with commentary in shorthand.
- Politics, vols. 3-5, circa 1887; Hoag, Spencer (Box 1)
  Three volumes of politics clippings from Brooklyn newspapers. Volume 3 has an index at the front.
- [Clippings], circa 1850s-1880s; Brewster, Laura M. (Box 2)
  Brewster, Laura M.
- Miscellaneous Historical Notes, 1929-1951 (Box 2)
  Clippings related to historic buildings in the Northeast region of the United States.
- Poems by Bloodgood Cutter, 1861-1895 (Box 2)
  Cutter, Bloodgood H. (Bloodgood Haviland)
- [Eagle clippings], 1907-1909; Fina, Donald P. (Box 2)
  Four volumes of clippings from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle. There are two volumes with clippings related to vital statistics (obituaries, marriage announcements etc.) and one each on real estate and transit.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  These scrapbooks appear to have been compiled by Donald P. Fina, although one label reads "Don Frica."
- Clippings of portraits and cartoons of the Beecher-Tilden Trial, 1875; Morris & Pearsall (Box 3)
- Park Theatre Broadsides, 1863-1864; Harrison, Gabriel (Box 3)
  Harrison, Gabriel
- Parkway System - New York City and Long Island (Box 4)
  Black and white photographs documenting the construction of various parkways around New York City and Long Island. Also includes one folded map at front.
- Loomis Havemeyer vacation scrapbook, 1902 (Box 5)
  Documents a 1902 trip to Europe taken by Brooklyn resident Loomis Havemeyer (1886-1971) and his family.
- Prospect Park Centennial scrapbook, 1966 (Box 6)
  "To Robert E. Blum from Jack [Ray; coordinator] and [Miss] Jimi [Kadrey; assistant]." Contains correspondence, clippings, photographs and ephemera as well as an original centennial flag.
- [Preutz scrapbook], 1930-1974 (Box 7)
  This scrapbook has multiple pieces of correspondence loose at front addressed to Alex E. Preutz. It contains clippings and ephemera related to New York City politics and sports as well as military and veteran news (primarily circa 1940s-1950s). Loose at the front is one issue of New York News magazine, October 13 1974.
- Kings County Historical Society scrapbook, circa 1911-1920 (Box 7)
  Ephemera and publications from the Kings County Historical Society.
  Kings County Historical Society
- Brooklyn Theatre Fire scrapbook compiled by Augustus Toedteberg, 1876; Toedteberg, Augustus (Box 8)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  A photocopied version of this scrapbook is available in the library under the call number F129.B7 B768 1876p and should be used in place of this original if possible.
- [Coney Island] Mardi Gras "Frolics of 1924", 1913-1924 (Box 9)
  Scrapbook of clippings related to Coney Island Mardi Gras, 1924. One photograph of Coney Island Mardi Gras Executive Committee, 1913. One letter from Coney Island Business Men's Club, undated.